Guide to the Administrative Papers of University College of Arts and Science, Office of the Dean RG.18.0.2
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the Dean, University College of Arts and Science (Archibald L. Bouton)
1899-1941
New York University Archives
New York University. College of Arts and Science. Office of the Dean
RG.18.0.2
7.5 Linear Feet
Collection contains correspondence of Professor of Rhetoric (1905-1914) and English (1914-1941), and Dean of University College of Arts and [Pure] Science (1914-1935), Archibald L. Bouton. Also included are transcripts of lectures, exam questions, course outlines, essays and articles written by Bouton many of which concern World War I (1914-1918) and the role of the University in student mobilization for the conflict.
Biographical Information
Archibald Lewis Bouton was born on September 1, 1872 in Cortland, New York. He received his A.B. from Amherst in 1896 and his M.A. from Columbia in 1900. He first came to New York University in 1898 as an instructor of English. In 1901 he became an assistant professor, and then a full professor in 1905. In 1914 Bouton became head of the English department and also the Dean of the College of Arts and Pure Science.
As a teacher and as an administrator, Bouton was deeply involved with the people and the events around him. Even while he was Dean, Bouton remained active as an instructor and a scholar. In 1916 he took a year's leave of absence to study at Harvard. Marshall S. Brown took over his duties as Dean for this time. Bouton used his summers to be a guest lecturer at various schools: the University of California in 1925, and the University of Colorado in 1927-1930.
As an administrator, Bouton dealt with the events that occurred during the important years of 1914-1935. In 1919 Bouton wrote a pamphlet entitled "The Colleges and Americanism." Here he set forth the idea that American institutions of higher learning had to inculcate values of Americanism in their students. To do so, it was first necessary to find a specific "type" of student who could also maintain the high level of academic performance that his school might require. This pamphlet written by Bouton and the subsequent actions of University Administration led to the creation of the selective admissions policy at University College in 1919. A policy of selective admissions was without precedent in the United States, and called for the taking of a psychological test, an appearance before a personnel board and an oath of loyalty before a student could be admitted at the University Heights College.
On a more personal level, Bouton was involved in the Century Club and was a founder and Vice-President of the Society of the Friends of the University of Rome. He made several trips abroad, studying, meeting with alumni, and relaxing. Such a rest trip was taken in 1931-1932. Arthur Hill became Acting Dean for this period. Bouton had earlier (1923-1924) taken a sabbatical, leaving Perley Thorne to act as Dean in his absence. Finally in 1935, Bouton was forced to take another leave, this time for health reasons. Arthur Hill again stepped in for him until Irving Berg was appointed Dean in 1936.
Once recovered, Bouton concentrated on his teaching and became the Director of the Elmer Ellsworth Brown House for English Studies. Bouton died on April 18, 1941 (in Pasadena, California) after having been Dean of University College for twenty-one years, Acting Dean of the Graduate School for 1925-1927, and a teacher for forty-three years.
Sources:
Chancellor's Reports, 1914-1935, New York University.
Jones, Theodore Francis, ed., New York University 1832:1932, New York: New York University Press, 1933.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged alphabetically by subject
The records have been organized into two series:
1. Correspondence
2. Lectures Notes, Writings, Addresses and Publications.
Separated Material
Some oversized materials have been removed from Box 1 and placed in flat storage. Separation sheets in the folders indicate where these materials were originally located.
Related Material at the New York University Archives
Records of the Students' Army Training Corps, 1916-1921
Bouton, Archibald L., Biographical File
Bouton, Archibald L., Portrait File
Brown, Elmer Ellsworth, 1861-1934, Papers
MacCracken, Henry Mitchell, 1852-1910, Papers
Bryans, William Remington, 1884-1974, Papers
Snow, Charles Henry, 1863-1957, Papers
Jones, Theodore Francis, 1885-, Papers
Balliet, Thomas M., 1852-1942, Papers
Dean Bouton, just prior to his death, donated a small collection of rare books to New York University now part of the Fales Collection.
Scope and Content
Series I: Correspondence, 1914-1935, is an alphabetical subject file consisting of correspondence, memoranda, news clippings, and charts. It includes material on such diverse topics as departments within the University, property and facilities operated by the University, as well as extensive information concerning World War I. This chronicles the University's involvement and participation with the U.S. Military during and after World War I. Of special note are Bouton's correspondence concerning the relationships between the University, the military, and the public as a result of the war. Also of importance during this time period is the University's involvement with the Students' Army Training Corps and the Reserve Officer Training Corps which was an outgrowth of the University's experience with the S.A.T.C. How students felt about the University and its military involvement is reflected in correspondence with the Dean. Also included is material concerning selective admissions, the use of personnel and psychological testing, loyalty oaths, and their relationship towards using higher education to inculcate Americanizing influences upon students.
Series II: Lecture Notes, 1899-1915; Writings, Addresses, and Publications, 1909-1941, is a chronological file consisting of fragments of lectures, exam questions, and course outlines. Included are Lecture Notes taken by Bouton in a graduate course he attended at Columbia University. Taught by Professor Robinson in 1899-1900 the course was entitled, "History XI." Bouton became the professor of History of English Literature at New York University in the years 1911-15 and Lecture Notes for several courses are included in this series. Also included are Writings and Addresses, 1914-1921. Publications, 1909-1934 consist of a chronological arrangement of articles, essays, and pamphlets written by Bouton.
Note! Look for a particular professor's correspondence under both the individual's name and department.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
This collection is in off-site storage.
Provenance
The alphabetical subject files of Archibald L. Bouton, Dean of University College from 1899-1941, came from the Office of the Dean of University College and were transferred to the University Archives from the University Heights Campus when the campus closed in 1973.
Memorandums.; New York (N.Y.).; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); World War, 1914-1918; Correspondence.; Syllabi.; Eulogies; Lecture notes.; New York University; MacCracken, Henry Mitchell, 1840-1918; Brown, Elmer Ellsworth, 1861-1934; Jones, Theodore Francis, 1885-1968; United States. Army. Students' Army Training Corps; New York University. Faculty of Arts and Science; Snow, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1863-1957; Bouton, Archibald Lewis, 1872-1941; Balliet, Thomas M. (Thomas Minard), 1852-1942; Bryans, William Remington, 1884-1974; The Elmer Ellsworth Brown House for English Studies; New York University -- History -- 20th century; New York University. College of Arts and Science; New York University. University College of Arts and Pure Science; United States. Army. Reserve Officers' Training Corps -- History
- Series I: Correspondence, 1914-1935
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, 1914-1935, is an alphabetical subject file consisting of correspondence, memoranda, news clippings, and charts. It includes material on such diverse topics as departments within the University, property and facilities operated by the University, as well as extensive information concerning World War I.
  - Correspondence: A, 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abbott, James, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Directives to Instructional Staff, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Admission: Qualifications (see also: Selective Admission.. .), 1914-1922 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alliance Francaise, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - All Year School Schedule, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1926-1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Council on Education: Students War Service Campaign, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American Red Cross, 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Amherst Williams Wesleyan Debate, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Andrews, Charlton, 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Anti Semitism, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual Report: Charts, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ashley, Dean Clarence D., 1915 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Association of Colleges and Universities, New York, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Audubon Books, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: "B", undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Balliet, Dean Thomas M., 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Babcock, Professor Earl B., 1915 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Banking Fellowship, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bardwell, Darwin L., 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Barney, Kerson W., 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Barr, Jean, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Biology, Department of, includes letters from the Bursar and Properties Supervisor concerning the department, 1916-1932 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Black Students (note from W.E.B. DuBois' "The Crisis" re: number of black students at University College), 1919 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bonner, Griffith, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bouton, Lewis, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bronx Board of Trade (formerly North Side Board of Trade), 1914-1920 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Brown, Constance P., 1914 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Brown, Elmer E., 1914-1915 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Brown, Elmer E., 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Brown, Marshall S., 1914-1916 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Briggs, Carey C.D., 1914-1916 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bristol, Professor Charles L., 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Bursar's Office, 1911-1914 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bursar's Office, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bursar's Office, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Bursar's Office, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bursar's Office, 1919-1920 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bursar's Office, 1921-1922 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bursar's Office, 1923-1925 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: "C", undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Cafeteria Service: Chart of Organization n.d., undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Calendar, 1917-1918 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Campus Concert Course, 1914-1918 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Calton and Mott, 1915-1918 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Cathedral of St. John the Divine, 1924-1927 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Century Club, 1920, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Chapel Attendance/Chapel Committee, 1914-1916 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Clapp, Professor Edwin J., 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Classical Professorship, 1912-1923 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - College Cruise Around the World, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Collins, George Rowland, 1919-1922 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Collins, Halsey M., 1916, 1919-1920 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Commerce Group, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Cosenza, Mario E., 1921-1922 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Counselor of Studies, including material on dropping the letter grade "E", 1927-1941 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Courtney, Arthur W., 1914-1919 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: "D", undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Darling, William L., 1916-1918, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Davis, A.B., 1915, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Davis, Royal J., 1917-1919 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Dean's Committee, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Delta Sigma Phi, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Demarest, Stanley T., 1914-1915 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - DeWitt, Benjamin P., 1914-1916 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Dillingham, J.D., 1920-1921 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Doggett, W. Kirk, 1914-1917 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Draper, John W., 1914-1921 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Draper, William H., Jr., 1914-1915, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: "E", undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Edmonds, Harry C., 1915-1922 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Edmondson, Thomas W., 1917-1921 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Emergency Relief Committee, concerning student employment, 1930-1934 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - English, Department of, includes material about appointments, programs, and correspondence with Homer A. Watt, 1916-1922 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - English, Department of-- primarily concerning the conference of British and American professors, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - English, Department of-- includes material about appointments, programs, correspondence with Arthur Nason and a questionnaire answered by Bouton on this Department, 1924-1926 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - English, Department of-- includes material about appointments and programs, 1927-1933 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Endowment Fund Campaign, 1917-1925 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Enrollment and Registration, 1914-1930 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Evander Childs High School, in regards to Freshmen Ducking Posters, etc., 1925-1926 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Evening Work at the Heights, 1928-1932 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: "F", undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Fang, Roland L., 1921-1922 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Farrell, James H., 1918-1920 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - French, J. Milton, 1921-1922 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: "G", undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Galezio, L.T., 1915-1918 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Galloway, Lee, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Garvin, Edwin L., 1919 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Gasparitsch, Edward, 1916-1918 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Gatens, Norman R., 1917 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - German, Department of, 1926-1933 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Gerstenberg, Professor Charles A., undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Geyser, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Gillett, Charles R., 1915-1916 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Gillett Memorial Library Fund, 1914-1915 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Glee Club, 1914-1915 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Golf Course (proposed), 1914 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Gould, John W. DuBois, 1914-1921 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Graduate School, 1914-1928 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Graduate School, 1929-1932 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Grey, Professor Henry D., 1915-1917, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Greenough, Chester M., 1918-1921 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Gymnasium Committee--Heights Campus, with Speeches and Agenda, 1926-1931 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: "H-He", undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: "Hi-Hy", undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Hall of Fame, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Hartley, Lyman R., 1918-1921 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Hathaway, Henry C., 1919-1922 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Hawkes, Herbert E., 1918-1922 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Heaton, Harry C., 1914-1921 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Hembdt, Phil H., 1914-1922 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Hering, Daniel W., 1914-1920 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Hill, Arthur E., 1914-1922 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Hotchkiss, George B., 1914-1915, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Hubbard, John C., 1916, 1918-1920 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Huntley, Willis A., 1914-1919 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Hymn books, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: "I", undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Ideas for Postwar Role of Colleges, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Independent Club of the West Side, 1915-1916 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Irwin, John V., 1917-1921 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: "J", undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Jackson, Dr. Holmes C., 1914-1916 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Jenkins, Raymond, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Johnson, Dean Joseph French, 1915-1921 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Jones, Theodore Francis, 1915-1921 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Junior Year Abroad, 1928-1936 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence: "K", undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Kittredge, George Lyman, 1915-1921 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Kotler Case(Ducking), 1915 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Kraemer, Casper J., 1915, 1918-1920 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: "L", undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Lamont, Colonel William, 1915-1919 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Langland, Howard F., 1920-1921 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Lauer, Emory J., 1914-1915, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Law, Dr. Frederick H., 1914-1920 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Lawrence, Richard W., 1915-1918 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - League of Nations, 1919 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - League to Enforce Peace, 1918-1919 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Leonard, William E., 1916-1919 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Lewin, Albert Parsons, 1915-1918 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Library, 1914-1933 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Limouze, Reverend Arthur H., 1914-1922 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Loomis, Milton E., 1915-1922 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Lott, J.H., 1917-1920 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Lough, Dr. James E., 1914-1921 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Lowes, Dr. John L., 1914-1919 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Lumbard, John W., 1915 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: "M", undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - MacCracken, Henry Mitchell, Chancellor Emeritus, 1913-1920 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - MacCracken, Dr. John H., 1913-1920 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - MacDonald, Charles, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Mackler, Harry S., 1918-1920 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Madden, John T., 1918-1920 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Magrath, A. Jocelyn H., 1921 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Marra, Ubaldo J., 1915-1919 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Marshall, William Jones, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Mayor's Committee on National Defense, 1916-1918 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - McCrady, Louisa, 1919-1921 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - McDonald, Philip B., 1919-1922 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - McDowell, Richard, 1915-1921 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - McEvoy, Thomas J., 1914-1915 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - McKibben, Frank P., 1918 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - McLouth, Lawrence A., 1914-1922 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Mead, Frederick S., 1918-1920 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Medical Preparatory Certificate, Medical College, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Medical Preparatory Course, Medical College, 1914-1916 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Medical Preparatory Course, Medical College, 1917-1919 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Medical Preparatory Course, Medical College, 1920-1930 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Meleney, Clarence E., 1915 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Military Discipline: Case Study, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Military Discipline: Student Subject to, 1918-1920, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Military Science and Tactics, Department of, 1929-1933 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Miller, Charles O., 1917-1918 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Miller, Cyrus C., 1915-1922 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Miller, Isador, 1915-1917 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Moore, Thomas John, 1918-1920 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Munn, Glenn E., 1917-1921 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Munn, James B.(see also: English, Department of), 1916, 1921-1922 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Murphy, Albert J., 1921 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence: "N", undated (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Nason, Arthur Huntington (see also:English, Department of), 1914-1922 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - National Food-Pledge Campaign, 1917 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Neuman, Dorothy, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Neumann, Joshua H., 1922 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - New York, 1927 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - New York Globe, 1920 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - New York Peace Society, 1915 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - New York University Preparatory School Day Committee, 1915 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - New York University Press, 1915, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - New Yorker, 1915-1922 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Newark Institute of Arts and Science, 1916-1917 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Newark Junior College, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Nichols, Archibald J., 1917-1920 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: "O", undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Oken, Nathaniel, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: "P", undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Paltsits, Victor H., 1915-1921 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Pang, Clinton Mindil, 1915-1921 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Park, Dean William H., 1914-1915 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Partisch, W.O., 1916-1920 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Patterson, Samuel W., 1915 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Pedagogy, School of, 1916-1919 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Pegues, Albert Shipp, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Pelton, Dewitt L., 1914-1918 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Personal Letters, 1916-1922 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Personal Efficiency Course, 1914-1918 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1915-1916, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Philosophy, Department of, 1927-1932 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Physical Training, 1914-1916 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Platt, Clarence M., 1915 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Powers, Wallace F., 1918 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Plattsburg SATC Training Program, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Pratt, William O. (Pratt Teachers Agency), 1914-1921 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Property, Supervisor of (Walter Cleverdon), 1915-1922 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Property, Supervisor of (Walter Cleverdon and Andrew Peterson), 1925-1933 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Psi Upsilon, NYU Chapter of, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Psychology, Department of, 1928-1929 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: "Q", undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Quimby, Ernest S., 1918-1921 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: "R", undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Recorder's Office, 1913-1920 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Recruitment, 1915-1918 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Reed, Harold L., 1919 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Report of the Committee Appointed to Reorganize the Curriculum of the Washington Square College, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Report of Committee on the Reorganization of the Collegiate Division, 1913 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Revell, F.H. and Company, 1916 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Rhees, Rush, 1917-1922 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Rich, S.G., 1914-1915 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Roberts, Vincent, 1918-1921 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Robertson, Samuel E. (President of Newark Institute of Arts and Sciences), 1914-1915 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Robinson, William J., 1914-1917 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Rollins, Hyder E., 1919-1922 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Roll of Honor, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, 1916 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Roosevelt Memorial Association, 1919-1920 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Rosenkampff, Arthur H., 1916-1918 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Rosenwald, Julius, 1915-1916 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Rotary Club of the Bronx, 1920-1921 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - ROTC: Establishment, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - ROTC: Operations, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - ROTC: Operations, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - ROTC: Operations, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - ROTC: Operations, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - ROTC: Operations, 1922-1928, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Rowe, Ivan H., 1920-1922 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Rubin, Morris L., 1919 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Rushmore, Harold S., 1919-1921 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: "Sa-Si", undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: "Si-Sy", undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Sacks, Maxwell L., 1918 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Sandham, Anna, 1916-1918 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Saperstein, David/Samuel, 1917,1920-1921 (Box 12, Folder 3)